Guide to the Charles Colcock Jones Papers, 1757-1926
David M. Rubenstein Rare Book & Manuscript Library Duke University Durham, N.C., USA
Charles Colcock Jones papers 1757-1926
David M. Rubenstein Rare Book & Manuscript Library, Duke University
Jones, Charles Colcock, 1831-1893
4.5 Linear Feet approx. 920 Items
Jones was a lawyer, collector, Confederate soldier and historian from Savannah, GA.
Collection includes correspondence, journals, commonplace books, lecture notes, scrapbooks, autograph albums and other papers. The material ranges in date from 1757-1926.
Administrative Information
Access Restrictions
Collection is open for research.
Researchers must register and agree to copyright and privacy laws before using this collection.
All or portions of this collection may be housed off-site in Duke University's Library Service Center. The library may require up to 48 hours to retrieve these materials for research use.
Please contact Research Services staff before visiting the David M. Rubenstein Rare Book & Manuscript Library to use this collection.
Provenance
The Charles Colcock Jones Papers were acquired by the David M. Rubenstein Rare Book & Manuscript Library as between 1941-1958.
Biographical Note
Charles Colcock Jones, Jr. was born October 28, 1831 in Savannah, GA to a Presbyterian Minister. He graduated from Princeton University in 1852 and received a law degree from Harvard University in 1855. That same year, Jones returned to Savannah and was elected mayor in 1860. Jones served in the Confederate army during the Civil War and moved to New York City after the war to rebuild his lost fortune. In 1877, Jones returned to Georgia where he began to write and publish books about Georgia's history and collecting historical materials. He died in 1893.
Collection Overview
The collections contains correspondence, journals, commonplace books, lecture notes on literature, natural philosophy, and physics, scrapbooks, addresses, autograph albums, and other papers, many dealing with the collecting of historical materials. Many letters from famous literary and civic figures are in acknowledgment of copies of Jones' books. Other subjects include Washington's Indian policy; hardships of travel to and life in California in the mid-19th century; Union volunteer generals of foreign birth; numbers of troops furnished to the U.S. Army by certain states (1861-1865); campaigns, battles, and conditions during the Civil War; manufacturing in Georgia; militia in Chatham Co., Ga., during the Revolution; slavery; and abolitionists. Includes records of the Harvard Law School Moot Court, and the manuscript texts of Jones' The History of Georgia (1883) and of The History of the Church of God (1867) by Jones' father, Charles Colcock Jones. There are also two manuscript maps with information on the Battle of Savannah (29 Dec. 1778) drawn by Jones for his books Siege of Savannah and The Life and Services of the Honorable Maj. Gen. Samuel Elbert, of Georgia.
Subject Headings
These are searchable subject entries for this collection. Performing a search on these subjects in the Duke University Libraries online catalog will bring up other related research materials.
Jones, Charles Colcock, 1831-1893
Harvard Law School
United States. Army -- Officers
Abolitionists -- United States
Historians -- Southern States
Indians of North America -- Government relations -- 1789-1869
Slavery -- United States
Industries -- Georgia
California -- Description and travel
Chatham County (Ga.)--Militia
Georgia -- History -- Revolution, 1775-1783
Savannah (Ga.)--History -- 18th century
South Carolina -- History -- Revolution, 1775-1783
Southern States -- History -- Revolution, 1775-1783
United States -- History -- Civil War, 1861-1865 -- Campaigns
Related Material
Edgar G. Dawson Papers, 1845-1889
David M. Rubenstein Rare Book & Manuscript Library; Duke University
John Brown Gordon Papers, 1872-1949 (bulk 1877-1899)
David M. Rubenstein Rare Book & Manuscript Library; Duke University
Bibliography
Penn, Neil S.. Charles Colcock Jones Jr., Georgia Archaeologist, Collector and Historian. Master's Thesis (Durham, NC: Duke University, 1958).
Contents of Collection
- Correspondence Series, 1775-1907, undated, (3 boxes)
  - Correspondence, 1775-1872 (Box 1)
  - Correspondence, 1873-1886 (Box 2)
  - Correspondence, 1887-1907, undated (Box 3)
- Clippings and Printed Material Series, 1760-1888, (1 box)
  - Clippings, 1760-1888 (Box 4)
  - Printed Material, 1877-1886
- Addresses, Writings and Notes Series, 1807-1899, undated, (5 boxes)
  - Addresses and Writings (Miscellany), 1807-1899, undated (Box 5)
  - Casimir Pulaski
  - The Lovers of Ty-sing-pan
  - Negro Myth from the Georgia Coast Told in the Vernacular (Box 6)
  - Biographical Sketches of the Deligates from Georgia to the Continental Congress (Box 7)
  - Volumes [?]
  - Notes on the History of Georgia, 1730s-1770s (Box 8)
  - Notes (Miscellany)
  - Notes on the History of Georgia, 1780-1809 (Box 9)
- Other Papers and Oversize Series, 1757-1891, undated, (1-2 boxes plus folders)
  - Legal papers, 1757-1883 (Box 10)
  - Financial papers, 1763-1891
  - Military reports, 1863-1864
  - Miscellany
  - Pictures
  - Volumes [?]
  - Papers, 1764-1809 and manuscript maps of the Battle of Savannah (1778) (Opaperfolder 1)
  - Military reports (Opaperfolder 2)
  - Papers, 1852 [doublecheck stacks on this material - not listed in catalog] (Box 6th 17:C)
  - Georgia Portfolio, II (Box 11)
- Volumes Series, 1850-1894
  - Address on Sergeant Jasper before Hibernian Society, 1881, (53 pages) (Volume M-2005)
    Augusta, Ga.
  - Anicent Monuments of the Etowah Valley, read before Georgia Historical Society-A series, 1864-1865, (79 pages) (Volume L-2006)
    Savannah, Georgia
  - Autograph album used for classmates and professors at Princeton University, 1852 (Volume M-2007)
  - Commonplace Book, 1852, (309 pages) (Volume M-2008)
    Nassua Hall, Princeton, New Jersey
  - History of the Church of God (Vol. 1), 1854-1855, (276 pages) (Volume L-2010)
    Augusta, Georgia
  - History of the Church of God (Vol. 2), 1855-1856, (592 pages) (Volume L-2011)
  - History of the Church of God (Vol. 3), 1856-1860, (315 pages) (Volume L-2012)
  - History of the Church of God (Vol. 4), 1856-1858, (290 pages) (Volume L-2013)
  - History of the Church of God (Vol. 5), 1858-1860, (161 pages) (Volume L-2014)
  - History of Georgia, 1883, Vol. 1 Part 1 (Volume F-2015)
  - History of Georgia (1883), Vol. 1, Part 2 (Volume F-2016)
  - History of Georgia (1883), Vol. 2 Part 1 (Volume F-2017)
  - History of Georgia (1883), Vol. 2, Part 2 (Volume F-2018)
  - Journal, 1879 June 4-July 5, (150 pages) (Volume S-2019)
    Journal of a trip to Europe; description of journey from New York to Liverpool.
  - Journal, 1879 July 6-15, (125 pages) (Volume S-2020)
    Journal of a trip to Europe; London and its vicinity.
  - Journal, 1879 July 16- 26, (152 pages) (Volume S-2021)
    Journal of a trip to Europe; Northern England and Scotland.
  - Journal, 1879 July 27-Aug. 5, (152 pages) (Volume S-2022)
    Journal of a trip to Europe; Scotland, Belgium, Germany.
  - Journal, 1879 Aug. 16-17, (152 pages) (Volume S-2023)
    Journal of a trip to Europe; Germany, Austria, Italy.
  - Journal, 1879 Aug. 18-23, (151 pages) (Volume S-2024)
    Journal of at rip to Europe; Italy, Switzerland.
  - Journal, 1879 Aug. 24-Sept. 3, (121 pages) (Volume S-2025)
    Journal of a trip to Europe; Switzerland, France.
  - Journal, 1879 Sept. 4-16, (131 pages) (Volume S-2026)
    Journal of a trip to Europe; France.
  - Journal, 1879 Sept. 18-Oct. 15, (115 pages) (Volume S-2027)
    Journal of a trip to Europe; France, England, Homeward.
  - Lecture notes (Literature), 1850, (236 pages) (Volume M-2028)
    Princeton University, New Jersey
  - Lecture notes (Natural Philosophy), 1851, (300 pages) (Volume L-2029)
  - Lecture notes (Physics), 1851, (400 pages) (Volume L-2030)
  - Letter Press Copy Book, 1864, (500 pages) (Volume M-2031)
  - Letter Press Copy Book, 1864-1867, (1024 pages) (Volume L-2032)
    Location unknown, note on card says pages shattered.
  - Letter Press Copy Book, 1867-1869, (974 pages) (Volume L-2033)
    Wall Street, New York
  - Letter Press Copy Book, 1869-1870, (951 pages) (Volume L-2034)
    Augusta, Georgia; Missing
  - Letter Press Copy Book, 1870-1872, (994 pages) (Volume L-2035)
  - Letter Press Copy Book, 1872-1874, (999 pages) (Volume L-2036)
  - Letter Press Copy Book, 1874-1876, (995 pages) (Volume L-2037)
    Augusta, Georgia; pages shattering
  - Letter Press Copy Book, 1876-1877, (976 pages) (Volume L-2038)
  - Letter Press Copy Book, 1877-1878, (708 pages) (Volume L-2039)
  - Letter Press Copy Book, 1877-1881, (552 pages) (Volume L-2040)
  - Letter Press Copy Book, 1878-1880, (696 pages) (Volume L-2041)
  - Letter Press Copy Book, 1880, (708 pages) (Volume L-2042)
  - Letter Press Copy Book, 1881, (708 pages) (Volume L-2043)
  - Letter Press Copy Book, 1881-1883, (701 page) (Volume L-2044)
  - Letter Press Copy Book, 1881-1883, (500 pages) (Volume F-2045)
  - Letter Press Copy Book, 1883, (702 pages) (Volume F-2046)
  - Letter Press Copy Book, 1883-1884, (697 pages) (Volume F-2047)
  - Letter Press Copy Book, 1884-1885, (700 pages) (Volume F-2048)
  - Letter Press Copy Book, 1884-1885, (991 pages) (Volume F-2049)
  - Letter Press Copy Book, 1885-1886, (998 pages) (Volume F-2050)
  - Letter Press Copy Book, 1885-1889, (697 pages) (Volume F-2051)
  - Letter Press Copy Book, 1886, (994 pages) (Volume F-2052)
  - Letter Press Copy Book, 1886-1887, (989 pages) (Volume F-2053)
  - Letter Press Copy Book, 1887-1888, (999 pages) (Volume F-2054)
  - Letter Press Copy Book, 1888, (1000 pages) (Volume F-2055)
  - Letter Press Copy Book, 1888-1889, (997 pages) (Volume F-2056)
  - Letter Press Copy Book, 1889-1890, (697 pages) (Volume F-2057)
  - Letter Press Copy Book, 1889-1890, (996 pages) (Volume F-2058)
  - Letter Press Copy Book, 1890, (999 pages) (Volume F-2059)
  - Letter Press Copy Book, 1890-1891, (995 pages) (Volume F-2060)
  - Letter Press Copy Book, 1890-1893, (698 pages) (Volume F-2061)
  - Letter Press Copy Book, 1891-1892, (997 pages) (Volume F-2062)
  - Letter Press Copy Book, 1892-1893, (998 pages) (Volume F-2063)
  - Letter Press Copy Book, 1893-1894, (1004 pages) (Volume F-2065)
  - Occasional Addresses, 1882-1883; newspaper clippings, (130 pages) (Volume M-2066)
  - Records of Harvard Law School Moot Court, 1853-1854, (144 pages) (Volume M-2067)
  - Scrapbook; Antiquities of Georgia, 1877-1878, (75 pages) (Volume M-2068)
  - The Private Soldier of the Present Revolution, 1864, (47 pages) (Volume F-2069)
  - Autograph letters and portraits of the signers of the Constitution of the Confederate States, collected by Charles Colcock Jones, Jr., (151 pages) (Volume ff-756)
  - Original roster of general officers, War Dept.-Adjutant General's office, [1861-1865?], (65 pages) (Volume ff-775)